Guide to the Stanford University Publications and Ephemera Collection
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University publications and ephemera collection
1885-2014
SC4000
Stanford University -- General subdivision--History.;
1000 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Other Finding Aids
Additional info, including indices, availabline online here: http://purl.stanford.edu/qq422xt3553.
Biographical/Historical note
The Stanford University Archives was officially created in 1965 by the Board of Trustees, but active collection of historical materials had been in place prior to that date. One of the early attempts to catalog some of that material was a subject framework known as the "4digit" collection, now known as the publications and ephemera collection.
Scope and Contents note
This intentionally assembled collection contains publications, printed matter, and ephemera documenting Stanford University. This guide is a high level listing of the major subject headings that are used to organization the collection. These include: history of the founders and the university; administration; faculty; academic schools; graduate schools of law, medicine, and business; libraries; interdepartmental programs; athletics; students; alumni; and special topics, including local history.
Collection Contents
- History of the Founders, 0001-0099
  - Leland Stanford, 0001-0023
  - Jane L. Stanford, 0024-0049
  - Leland Stanford, Jr., 0050-0059
  - Stanford Family, 0060-0089
  - Lathrop Family, 0090-0099
- University History; Buildings and Grounds; Stanford Miscellany, 0100-0999
  - University Documents, 100
  - Opening day; dedication, 130
  - Special legislation relating to the University, 140
  - Court action relating to the University, 180
  - Buildings and grounds, general, 200
  - Architecture, general, 220
  - Construction; Goodrich quarry, 240
  - Buildings, individual, 0260-0299
  - Grounds, individual areas, 0300-0349
  - Historical events (including earthquake, wars), 0400-0699
  - Stanford miscellany, 0700-0999
- Administration, 1000-1999
  - Board of Trustees, 1000-1099
  - President, Office of the, 1100-1199
  - Vice President and Provost, 1200
  - Associate Provost for Research, 1205
  - Vice Provost and Dean of Undergraduate Studies/Vice Provost for Undergraduate Education, 1210
  - Vice President for Finance, 1220
  - Controller, 1230-1249
  - Vice President for Business Affairs (including police, fire, telephone system), 1250-1259
  - Business Manager, 1260
  - Plant Services, 1269
  - Personnel and Employee Relations, 1280-1289
  - Stanford University Press (except Press books - see 9950), 1290-1295
  - Real Estate Manager, 1300
    see also Land Development, 9150
  - Development, 1320-1399
  - Undergraduate Education (see also 1210), 1400-1499
  - Graduate Division, 1500-1599
  - Accreditation and other evaluative reports, 1600
  - Summer School, 1650-1660
  - Tours and Guided Tours, 1676
  - Public relations publications about the University, 1680
  - News and Publications Services, 1685
  - Stanford Publication Services, 1687
  - Dean of Student Affairs, 1720-1724
  - Admissions, 1750
  - Registrar, 1760-1799
  - Career Planning and Placement Center, 1800-1806
  - Financial Aid, 1810
  - Overseas Campuses, 1840-1859
  - Health Services (including Cowell Health Center, counseling services), 1880
- Faculty, 2000-2499
  - Faculty - general, 2000
  - Faculty Housing, 2001
  - Faculty Awards, 2007
  - Faculty Men's Club, 2045
  - Joint Faculty Club, 2060
  - Undergraduate Specials sponsored by Member of the Academic Council, 2070
  - Faculty Social and Academic Organizations, 2160
  - Faculty Organization (including Articles of Tenure), 2170-2179
  - Academic Council (see also SC0193), 2180-2193
  - Judicial Committees and Panels, 2194-2199
  - Faculty Advisory Board (including Faculty Grievance Panel), 2200
  - Endowed Professorships, 2210
  - Emeritus Faculty, 2400
  - Special University-wide Committees (including Committee of 15), 2260
  - Books by Faculty, 2499
- Schools (except Law, Medicine, and Business), 2500-4999
  - Earth Sciences, 2500-2749
  - Education, 2750-2999
  - Engineering, 3000-3399
  - Humanities and Sciences, 3400-4999
- School of Law, 5000-5299
  - Law School Commencement, 5012
  - Law Student Organizations, 5014
  - Fund Raising and Development, 5030
  - Law Buildings, 5060-5065
  - Law School Library, 5075
  - Law Alumni, 5200
- School of Medicine, 5300-5699
  - Fund Raising and Development, 5350
  - Medical Center News Bureau, 5360
  - Lane Medical Library, 5375
  - Commencement, 5449
  - Medical Alumni, 5450
  - Departments of the School of Medicine, 5500
  - Divisions of the School of Medicine, 5540-5570
  - Medical School of the Pacific, 5600
  - Toland Medical School, 5605
  - Cooper Medical College, 5610
  - Lane Hospital, 5620
  - Palo Alto Hospital, 5630
  - Hoover Pavilion, 5640
- Graduate School of Business, 5700-5999
  - GSB Buildings, 5705
  - Jackson Library, 5775
  - Conferences and Special Programs, 5800
  - GSB Alumni, 5900
- Library (Main; Green; Meyer), 6000-6499
  For coordinate libraries see appropriate department
  - Library (general material), 6000-6074
  - Library Buildings, 6075-6099
  - Acquisitions, 6100-6104
  - Binding and Finishing, 6105-6109
  - Gifts and Exchange, 6110-6114
  - Serials, 6115-6119
  - Cataloging, 6120-6125
  - Circulation, 6140-6144
  - Departmental Libraries - general material only, 6170
  - Government Documents, 6200-6205
  - Reference (Formerly Humanities and Social Science), 6220-6225
  - Resources Development, 6240
  - Science Division, 6250
  - Special Collections, 6270-6289
  - Technical Information Services, 6290
  - Undergraduate Library (Meyer), 6300-6314
  - Stanford Collection, 6315-6319
  - University Archives, 6320
  - Library Staff, 6330-6345
  - Library Automation Project (Project BALLOTS), 6350
  - Job Classification Project, 6354
  - Business Services, 6360
  - Photocopy Facilities, 6361
  - Hopkins Transportation Library, 6400-6404
  - Library Development Committee, 6442
  - Miscellaneous Publications regarding the Library, 6451
- Departments and Programs-Interdepartmental; Athletics, 6500-6999
  - Miscellaneous examinations, 1913-1917, 6501
  - Biophysics Laboratory, 6520
  - Special Inter-School Programs, 6525
  - Stanford Center for Information Processing (SCIP), 6540-6545
  - Food Research Institute, 6560-6575
  - Hoover Institute, 6580-6609
  - High Energy Physics Laboratory, 6630
  - Hydrology, 6650
  - Center for Interdisciplinary Research, 6655
  - Institute for Mathematical Studies in Social Sciences, 6670
  - Stanford-NDEA Institute for Teachers of German, 6680
  - Institute for the Study of Human Problems, 6690
  - Microwave Laboratory, 6710
  - Operations Research Program, 6730
  - Physical Education for Men (pre-1975), 6750
  - Physical Education for Women (pre-1975), 6770
  - Dept. of Athletics, Physical Education and Recreation (1975-), 6780
  - Inter-University Program for Chinese Language Students in Taipei, 6790
  - Inter-University Center for Japanese Study in Tokyo, 6801
  - Stanford Linear Accelerator Center (SLAC), 6810-6814
  - Typing and Shorthand, 6850
  - Research Groups Located at Stanford But Not Supported by Stanford (alphabetical), 6860-6899
- Students, 7000-7999
  - Undergraduates, 7000-7159
  - Graduate Students, 7160-7174
  - Student living and eating groups--general material, 7200
  - Sororities, 7220-7239
  - Fraternities, 7240-7259
  - Eating Clubs, 7260
  - Food Service, 7264
  - Student housing--residences, 7280-7460
  - Student Dependent Services, 7461
  - Student government--general material, 7470
  - Academic programs sponsored by students (includes SCIRE, SWOPSI, SPIF), 7520
  - Student Unions, 7550
  - Book Store, 7570
  - KZSU, 7591
  - International Students, 7593-7599
  - Honor Societies, 7600
  - Men's Organizations (including YMCA), 7650
  - Women's Organizations (not including YWCA), 7700
  - Student organizations--General, 7750
  - YWCA, 7751
  - Student-Sponsored Non-Academic Programs, 7755
  - Musical Groups, 7800-7839
  - Dramatics Groups, 7840-7879
  - Debate, 7880
  - Student Publications, 7900-7984
- Alumni, 8000-8499
  - Alumni Association, 8000-8100
  - Winds of Freedom Foundation, 8122
  - New Founders League, 8125
  - Class Yearbooks, Reunions, Directories, 8300-8310
  - Publications, 8450
- Athletics
  Through 1975; after that see 6780
  exceptions noted
  - Intercollegiate Athletics, 8500
  - Books Concerning Stanford Athletics, 8507
  - Stanford Buck Club (continued on past 1975), 8540
  - Athletic Buildings, 8600-8609
  - Miscellaneous Programs and Conferences, 8610
  - Athletic Fields (continued on past 1975), 8615
  - Stanford Axe (continued on past 1975), 8650
  - Stanford Indian, the (continued on past 1975), 8655
  - Cardinal (color) (continued on past 1975), 8656
  - Stanford Hall of Fame (continued on past 1975), 8660
  - Athletic Awards (continued on past 1975), 8665
  - Organization of Women Athletes (OSA), 8681
  - Sports and Contests, 8700-8980
- Special, Including Non-Stanford Material of Interest to Stanford, 9000-9999
  - Special Endowed Lectureships, 9000-9019
  - Conferences, Non-Stanford, Held on Campus, 9020
  - Student Conferences by Joint Stanford Groups, 9030
  - Student Conferences, Non-Stanford, Held on Campus, 9040
  - Sports (non-Stanford) on Campus, 9045
  - Industrial Affiliates Program, 9050
  - Stanford Research Institute (SRI International), 9100
  - Foundations, 9110
  - Residential Housing on Stanford Lands, 9120
  - Cedro Cottage, 9130
  - Land Development - General, 9150
  - Airport on Campus, 9153
  - Stanford Industrial Park, 9170
  - Stanford Shopping Center, 9180
  - Stanford Barn (the Winery), 9181
  - Palo Alto Square, 9182
  - Campus Elementary School, 9185
  - Campus Child Care Center, 9187
  - Medical-Dental-Professional Complex (Welch Road), 9190
  - Post Office, 9200
  - Stanford Inn, 9210
  - Kingscote Gardens, 9220
  - Children's Convalescent Home, 9230
  - Golf Course and Clubhouse, 9240
  - Free University of Palo Alto (Mid-Peninsula Free U.), 9250
  - Peninsula Observer, 9255
  - The Grapevine, 9256
  - per/se, 9257
  - Peace Corps, Vista, 9260
  - The Experiment, 9270
  - Esalen Program, 9271
  - Community for Relevant Education, 9273
  - Stanford Speakers Bureau, 9275
  - Population and Environment Forum, 9279
  - Local History of Interest to Stanford, 9800-9869
    - Palo Alto, 9800
    - Eadweard Muybridge, 9820
    - Land Development Near Stanford, 9840
    - Searsville and Ladera Dam, 9850
    - Mayfield, 9855
    - College Terrace, 9856
    - Menlo Park (includes Alpine Inn), 9860
    - San Francisquito Creek, 9861
    - Los Altos, 9862
    - Woodside, 9863
    - San Jose, 9870
  - Guidebooks not produced by Stanford, 9930
  - Stanford Press Books, 9950
  - Stanford Press Periodicals, 9951
  - L.S.J.U. Publications--University Series, 9952